I am Anabel González,
a psychiatrist from A Coruña.
I work in public health
and have written some
popular books.
The last one isWhere does it come from?,
a book that focuses,
above all, on fear
and how to develop the security
that can help us with it.
Hello, Annabelle.
I am Rafael Fernández Campos,
doctor in Economics and Public Finance
from the Autonomous University of Madrid.
Professionally, I work with data.
But the real reason I
wanted to be here with you today
is because I am a father of three children.
When you become a parent, it
seems like fear begins
to become part of your life.
Yes, having children is a
more complicated career than the other one, right?
-I think so.
-Yes.
Many
very natural fears arise with children
because the child needs to be with us
to feel protected
and we are the ones who should be afraid
for them,
but not so much fear that it blocks us
and prevents us from enjoying ourselves
and having good times.
Anabel, you are a psychotherapist.
You are a doctor of medicine.  You are a psychiatrist.
You've written several books,
but there's one in particular
that deals with fear.
I would like you to explain to me
how
these fear mechanisms work.
Fear is part
of our basic survival pack.
There are many animals
that have these kinds of emotions,
and human beings, without fear,
would have become extinct a long time ago.  This is what
makes
the body start moving if we face danger:
"We start the car engine
in case we have to run away."  What
happens is that, later, fear,
which is functional, good and necessary,
can become complicated for us,
precisely because of the things
our brain does
to try to do its job.
For example,
how do I know that something is dangerous?
At first, new things will scare
me just in case,
and the brain sometimes goes
a bit overboard with the "just in case" thing.
Then, everything
around me that scared me
will start to scare me.
I was bitten by a dog and I
was in an area of trees.
Now, when I get close to the trees, I'll say,
"What if a dog comes?",
and before I didn't think about it.
Then,
fear becomes associated with other things
and the brain doesn't do it because it is, it does it so
that we are prepared.  What
happens is that sometimes
we prepare a little too much.
Then, that's when
all this stuff we call anxiety,
panic... starts to happen,
which is when things get out of hand.
Understood, understood.
With this anxiety thing, it
seems like we have an epidemic now,
no matter the age.
You, in one of your books,
call anxiety
"the fear that sticks with you."
How did you find this happy phrase?
Well, that's a bit of it.
Fear sticks
to what is
around what is truly dangerous.
And anxiety would be that I
even think about things that could happen,
because anxiety, when it gets out of hand,
already makes you think
about the worst possibilities
that could happen
and, in addition,
you get anxious as if they were inevitable
and as if you couldn't do anything.
Then, there's a ladder,
more fear, more catastrophic thoughts,
and you end up in panic.
And here you can't think
about anything at all.
Here, the part of the brain that thinks,
which is what we have here, is
taken out of the equation.  We
can also reverse this.
There are therapies that work
to untie the knot that has formed.
There is an experiment
to manufacture a phobia,
which is an experiment
that today would not be ethical
or approved, by Watson,
who made a child
have a phobia of mice.
The boy liked mice, they
were funny to him,
but they started making a sudden noise
every time a mouse appeared
and the boy ended up being
afraid of mice,
which, in principle, he didn't have any.
I think they
didn't take it out on the poor guy afterwards, he
was left
with a fear of mice.
How does this translate
into what can happen to any of us?
Sometimes, there
's something there that's neutral,
that's harmless,
that's not a problem,
but something
scary happens to us next to that
and the brain says,
"That was here, I'll keep it.
That's scary too."
And this, which is not dangerous,
may continue to scare me,
perhaps, for the rest of my life,
and condition me when it comes to doing things.
And when I start to function like this,
sometimes
this can also become generalized.
Then, I
became increasingly afraid of more and more things.
In fact, there are people
who acquire a phobia
of leaving the house,
people who
literally stay locked in their homes
without any kind of lock
to prevent them from doing so
because everything,
absolutely everything, ends up scaring them.
It's something we call "agoraphobia."
And you say that there are therapies
that can unravel
this tangle?
Of course, because one of the mechanisms
that makes things worse,
not that it generates it,
but that it does make it worse,
is avoiding what scares us.
And it's logical, right?
If something has been dangerous, you say:
"I won't do it again."
But, if I don't do it again,
I'm more afraid of it.
And if it turns out that it's something I do have to
do...
I'm afraid to take the car
because I had a traffic accident,
but I have to take the car.
Then, I do everything:
I go with a friend, I take the bus...
But if one day I have to take the car,
then I will be a thousand times more afraid of it
because the fear has been eating away at me
and has been growing.
Then, some of the therapies
that work with this are getting
out of hand.
Sometimes, to get out of a maze,
the best way out is to
undo the path we have taken
to get to
where we are.  What
happens is that it's very lazy
because, once you've avoided a lot of things
and are so scared, it's
very difficult for you to
regain lost ground.
When you talk about trauma,
the fear of the past comes to mind.
Is it possible to be afraid of the past?
How can we face
the traumatic situations
we have suffered?
Sometimes, the past is hard
and we have survived
by never looking back.
We say,
"I'm moving forward and this has already happened,"
and it's like closing a chapter.
But, really,
if the things that have happened
still produce feelings in us,
it is because something has been blocked.
And these memories can influence us now
in many things.
I may be having a problem
with a coworker right now
because, perhaps,
I have had a similar experience
with a person in the past
that has nothing to do with this one,
and I am now unable to resolve it.
Then, when this happens,
we have to go back
because, if we don't untie this knot,
everything that happens
afterwards will get stuck too.
I work a lot with EMDR,
which is a type of trauma therapy,
and in it what is done
is to look for, precisely,
what the roots are.
I have a problem now.  I
may have a problem, for example,
in relationships.
Then,
we will look for what this is connected to.
The problem I have
is that I always end up in relationships
where I have to do what the other person wants,
and I, in the end,
end up giving up what I need.
We will go to the first relationships,
to see if
this pattern was created in these first relationships.
And then also to the first bonds,
which here we return
to childhood, to parents,
which is where we learn
to bond and connect.
My parents may have
loved me very much,
but I grew up
with a mother who was very sick
and I had to worry
about her more than they,
with the time they had
or the energy they had,
could worry about me.
So I got used
to giving up what I need
and I fit perfectly into couples
where I end up doing the same.
Then, what we would do would be,
these experiences
and the specific memories
in which
this problem has been formed,
we work on them one by one
and unblock them.
EMDR is called this because it uses,
among its ingredients,
systems to unlock memories.
One is eye movement.
The therapist would make this movement,
the patient follows the movement
and, by thinking about a traumatic memory
and doing this for a while,
of course, it
is a much more complex process, you
have to ask a series of things
and the therapist
has to help at certain times,
the memory loses strength.
If I have a memory of an accident,
for example,
years have passed and when I think about it it
still has
a very strong impact on me and I get anxious,
by doing this,
what I will notice when I return to the memory
is that the memory
becomes less intense.
And after a while,
every time I go back,
the feeling changes,
I can even see the most distant memory.
When something
has been engraved on us,
we are left with a very fixed image,
as it fades and there comes a time when
the memory loses all its strength
and, sometimes, it
can even be difficult to remember it.
Most of the time
we don't have such a clear memory.
Then,
when working on memories,
both of things that happened
and of what is activating us now,
because, perhaps, I had the problem
of the car accident
and now I get into it
and every time I do it I am afraid
or just think about getting into the car
and I am already afraid, we
also work
with the present and the future.
In this way,
the problems are cut from the root,
from all the experiences
that have to do
with the relationship problem
that I am having,
with the fear I have of driving
or with the problem that I have now.  What
is complex about this type
of treatment is finding where the root is.
Therefore, an exercise
that I sometimes propose is to look for,
when we were talking about fear,
what
our first experience of fear is,
what is the first memory
in which we remember being afraid.
And the second question would be:
"And am I still afraid?".
But it's not that I care much about it,
but when I think about it, it
's not a completely neutral memory.
If I stop for a while,
is the memory uncomfortable?
This would be an example of a memory
that is not processed.
And, by working on this memory, we
would begin to dry up the root of fear.
So now I could put myself
in the situations that are scaring me
with a much more proportionate fear.
Otherwise, sometimes,
I have a situation now
that scares me,
not so much because of the situation,
but because of the whole chain of things
that have been leaving
a little fear in my body.
So, now I have a fear
that I do
n't think is that big of a deal.
Why am I acting like this,
if what's happening
isn't of this caliber?
But still,
if I look back and link everything together,
all of this set of things
does explain the fear I have.  It
is proportionate to all of this,
not proportionate to this.
So, trauma therapies
work a bit like this.
In a way,
this is likeresetting yourbrain.
We have fears that are stuck,
that are blocked.
None of these fears are functional.
Functional fear is what I feel now,
when I have the lion in front of me.
It's this one.
But the lion I had ten years ago
no longer makes sense to continue here,
so what we do
is undo that influence.
The brain resetseverything
and puts it back in its place
as just another memory.
Many things
that used to scare us no longer scare us
because the brain has done this on its own.
Just as there are things
that disgusted us
at a certain time,
now, with the passage of time, they
no longer produce any sensation in us.
When this doesn't happen with a memory,
that memory
needs to be worked on.
And this is
one of the things we can do.  It
also helps, sometimes, to talk about it,
discuss it with other people,
listen to other perspectives...
But, in my experience,
EMDR works even with things
that we have talked about, that we have thought about
,
but this blockage is on a
more emotional, deeper level,
and this unlocks it
in a different way.
When we also talked about avoidance,
there are other types of trauma therapies
that work in a different way.
For example, what
exposure therapy does is:
this scares me,
and instead of avoiding it
and stopping doing things that trigger it, I
stay here.
So, at first,
I'm really scared, but I'm still here.
And then it scares me less,
and there comes a time when I get used to it.
It's like, "I'm afraid of the car.
I'll take it every day
until I get used to it again."
This is how fear can go away.
Then, in exposure therapy,
the person is in contact
with that difficult emotion
long enough for it to subside.
In EMDR, what is done is
that we connect with this situation,
and the person unlocks it
with eye movement
and things come to them,
things that may have to do with this
or may have to do
with these connections,
with these roots that we were talking about.
And, from time to time, we come back here,
just to do it again,
until all of this connects,
and here this gets smaller and smaller
and there's nothing left.
Later, I will
remember this situation again,
but it will be another experience.  It
will be part of my life wisdom,
my normal way of functioning.
My mother, it must be a good task.  I
understand that, in addition,
sometimes you refer to the blockages
and paralysis caused by fear.
In other words, it becomes a situation
of true paralysis.
How does this mechanism work?
How can it be untied and untangled?
When I was writing the book,
I asked a question
on social media
about what people associated with fear,
because fear itself is not a problem.
In fact, the other day someone told me:
"I'm never afraid."
Sorry, I'm afraid, everyone here has them, it
's impossible for you not to have them.  What
happens is
that we only call it "fear"
when fear blocks us,
when it gets us stuck,
and these are already associated problems.
So, this paralysis thing really
is a survival mechanism,
even if it doesn't seem like it,
but it can bother us quite a bit.
For example, when we
have a dangerous situation,
the car starts up in
case we have to run away,
in case we have to do something,
and the first responses are
active responses.  What
is logical is to fight
and, if I can't fight, I run away.
But if I can't fight
because the other person is bigger
and I can't run away because there's no way out,
and this happens a lot,
for example, when we're children,
because we can't face it,
run away, let's see where we go...,
the best solution is to stay still
because, if not, more will fall on you.
And if you see that staying still,
which would be paralysis, is
not getting you anywhere,
the body starts to say:
"I'll lower the revs. There
's no point in having the engine running
at full speed if there's nowhere to go,"
so we bow our heads, we submit...
You say, "Yes, yes"
to stop them from doing it again.
And the emergency response
is to collapse.
This is also
a survival mechanism.
In fact, if you are a herbivore, for example,
and a predator catches you,
the best thing you can do
is fall down
because then
the predator will think you are dead,
and a predator does
not eat dead prey.  It
is also survival for them.  They
could be eating
an animal in poor condition
or something dangerous to them.
So, if the animal is in a state
where it appears to be dead, it
survives.
Some authors call it a "defensive cascade",
and it is a response that is initially activated,
but when it sees
that there is no possibility,
it remains still and then goes down.
People, for example,
who suffer an assault, there
was a lot of talk
about sexual assaults,
believe that the only answer
is to be brave and fight.
And fighting is senseless
when you have no
chance of winning.
Becoming paralyzed
is a way to protect yourself.  Falling
down
is a way to protect yourself.
It is found in the survival instinct
of our species.
And this response of paralysis
or submission or collapse,
which are passive responses,
emergency responses,
those when there is nothing to do,
if they are repeated many times... We
said that children
Another response
a child has is to cry.
But if you're in a family
that doesn't meet your needs, you
end up not even crying.
A girl
who spoke on social media
about her experience
in an orphanage in Eastern countries explained
how children don't cry there, they
don't cry because why?
So, when you have lived
in a very hostile environment,
where there is no fighting,
no escaping, why cry?, you are
only left with the other answers.
And they are triggered so many times
that later, when you become an adult,
or if you have been in an abusive relationship,
for example,
or in a
very problematic situation for a long time, you
no longer know how to react
in any other way.
When you could fight, you don't fight anymore.
When you could walk away
from a problematic situation, you do
n't.  We
see this many times
in situations
of domestic violence,
which are people who, perhaps,
in their childhood stories, have
had very complicated childhoods,
and when they find themselves
in an abusive relationship, they
don't get out of it.
People sometimes look at them and say:
"But why didn't you leave earlier?".
If you've been blocked since childhood,
leaving is not easy at all.
The body knows how to do it,
but it's as if you've forgotten.
You need to remember again
how to get out of a situation,
that you can leave and that you can, sometimes,
fight for what you need.
And when we talk about fear
and the situations that scare us,
perhaps a very common
and very normal strategy would be to try to avoid them.
That is, not confronting them.  Do you
think these
fear avoidance strategies
are good, are they healthy
or can they have consequences later?
How do you see it?
To avoid it would be to escape.
If you are, for example,
with a partner who doesn't treat you well,
avoiding this relationship
would be the best thing you can do.
The problem is when we avoid things...
Sometimes, we avoid things
that are good for us.
Or we avoid everything,
and this starts
to make our lives very complicated.
All the mechanisms that the brain has,
including what happens in phobias,
are fundamentally something that makes sense.
It's the brain
putting itself in "just in case,"
it's the brain associating things
that could be dangerous.  What
happens is that,
sometimes, it slips out of our hands
or sometimes it appears where it doesn't belong
or stops being useful.
But everything our mind does is
for a reason.
Sometimes,
when we go back to the beginning,
if I think: "I'm paralyzed,
why am I paralyzed
at work with colleagues
if I'm an adult,
I have resources?
In other situations, I've been
able to manage it,
and now why not?".
Sometimes, the answer lies further back.
If I think:
"When was the first time I had
this feeling?",
things certainly
make a lot more sense here.
The thing is that this blockage has
stayed with me,
and when something happens
that the brain connects with it,
I get blocked again.
And that's how the brain thinks
all the time.
Me, if I'm in a meeting with you,
we're here talking,
our brains are connecting
with other conversations,
with other encounters..., we
won't be constantly reinventing ourselves.
But when the brain connects
with a blocking situation,
then...
If I reminded you of someone
you had
a bad experience with,
maybe right now you would be having
a strange feeling about me,
and maybe it would have nothing to do with me.
But the brain
is always associating things.  He
does it for our good.
But this
can sometimes backfire.
"The brain does it for our good."
I'll stick with this phrase, Anabel,
because, besides,
when you're next to someone
who happens to be afraid,
the phrase always comes out:
"Stay calm"
or "Stay calm",
"Don't be afraid".
As if this phrase were magical
and could solve fear.
These kinds of mantras, phrases,
which often seem to
provoke even more reaction,
is this a good mechanism?
What should we do in these situations,
when we are next to someone who
is suffering?
Of course, telling someone who has anxiety,
"Stay calm"
is like telling someone
who has a wound, "Don't bleed."
It's exactly the same.
In fact, people who have anxiety,
when they are told this, get angry
because they say:
"Of course, I would like it.
That is exactly what
I would like at this moment."  It
is true that the way
we talk
to ourselves has an influence.
In fact, people who have anxiety
say things to themselves
that make them even more afraid.
But, because the person
is saying these things to themselves, what
they are told from the outside
doesn't get through.
That's why we need to
do double the work.
Learn to say things
to others that will help them.
"Calm down" when he's
in an anxiety attack, no,
but you can tell him,
"I'm here. Do you
need anything? Can I help you?",
which won't make him feel bad
and we may not be able to perform miracles,
but it does help.
And then the same person
can learn
to see what things
can be said when it's wrong.
In the midst of a crisis it is difficult,
but afterwards
we can think a little.
Above all, more than whatever calms us down
at that moment,
which sometimes
means I need to see the doctor, have them
give me something to lower it,
and then we'll see
how we fix the issue,
work on developing,
above all,
the security that will make us
have less of this problem.
The most important thing is to develop
what could prevent this fear
and what can even help us get
through situations
that can cause us fear,
which is to have a greater sense of security.
Confidence does
n't mean you keep saying,
in a higher-than-normal tone of voice,
that you're very sure of what you're saying.
Quite the opposite.
Security comes from reflection,
from the ability to establish
relationships with others,
from trust...
Calm is fleeting.
I can do something that calms me down
at a certain moment,
but if the fear returns
shortly after, what do I do?
People who are afraid
sometimes find small solutions
that work in the short term,
like avoidance, which you mentioned earlier.
If I say: "I'm not going to this place,
it bothers me a bit,"
then that's fine, but what if you have to go there?
What if it
happens to you again later somewhere else?
There are things that can be avoided,
that solve the problem for the moment,
but that don't solve it later.
On the other hand, security is something
that we can gradually grow
until it helps us neutralize
fear a little
and, even if we are afraid, we
can do things.
There are things we do
even though they scare us
because we feel
that internal sense of security.
Security comes about
spontaneously
when you have grown up with people who have
given you protection and care.
And when I say this, I always want to insist
that we don't have to be perfect parents
and do everything right,
because that is horrible
for the safety of parents
and children.
We have to do it as best we can, but be there.
If I have a problem at school
or something happens to me with a friend
or I'm worried about
something that's happening at home
and someone notices it,
and I know that
if I have a problem, I can explain it,
I feel more confident, I
feel more secure,
I will feel that I can trust people.
Thanks to this,
if difficult things happen, I
won't be knocked down so easily.  We
all have a limit
and sometimes life
gets very complicated,
but I have more capacity
to deal with things.
Sometimes, life is very scary
and you need to have that feeling of
security to get through it.
Yes, yes.
You said a phrase earlier
that drove me crazy, that
"calm is fleeting."
So, if the calm is fleeting,
that means we will go through
stormy times.
Yes.  Is there
any way we can guarantee
or at least reasonably mitigate
these moments of anguish
and be able to have that security,
that confidence that you mention?
Sure, but how does
a sailor know he's safe?
Because he trusts
his abilities to do it,
because he has sailed many seas
of many different types, he knows
when to enter them and when not to, he
knows when to return to port,
which is also something that needs to be known.  He has
already been through a few storms,
learned from each one
and continues to go sailing.
If we keep doing things, from every mistake,
from every thing that goes wrong,
we learn,
and that is what makes us
feel that we have resources.  It's
not that we don't have to be afraid of anything.
If there is a huge storm, we should
not go out to sea.
It's very clear.
But I can feel
that I can handle many situations,
that I can navigate seas of different kinds.
And I feel like I can because I have
this feeling of security.
Anabel, if the antidote
to fear is security,
can we grow security?
Is there any way to make it grow?
Yes, but little by little.
Security must be sown, it
is something that grows little by little
and that has a lot to do
not only with us,
but it has a lot to do
with relationships.
Sometimes
we try to solve a problem
right where the problem is.  Let
's try...
I have a fever, I'll take something
to bring down my fever.
It's okay, it has to be done.
But what caused my fever?
Maybe it's an infection,
I need to take an antibiotic,
but I'm getting a lot of infections.
Shouldn't I strengthen my
immune system?
Growing security
is like strengthening
the emotional immune system
and is not so directly related
to what scares us, it
is background work.
For example, we said reflection.
Reflection is like state-of-the-art software
that makes everything that happens,
whether it goes well or badly, give
me more and more tools,
more and more resources.
I understand things better and better.  There
are still many things I don't understand, I
ask myself many questions
and feel very curious.
Curiosity
also increases security.
What Murakami said:
"Safety has a lot to do
with curiosity and courage."
He was talking, specifically, about curiosity
and courage, which went together.
Really, if you think about it,
a child feels curious
and this moves them
to do things that scare them,
but, because they are more curious
than afraid, they manage to do it.
Another thing that also increases
security is trust.
And this is complicated
because if we come, for example,
from stories of betrayal or stories
of very difficult relationships, let's
see who the handsome one is who trusts.  It
's not easy,
but you need to regain your confidence
because, if not, there's no chance.
A person who distrusts
is a person
who is placed inside a bunker
and, inside that bunker, you
may think that they won't hurt you,
but inside you ca
n't really feel safe.  We
feel safe when we walk down the street
and approach people,
we understand them,
when we connect with someone,
when we learn about things...
We need to explore
to feel safe.
How will we feel safe driving
if we always have our car in the parking lot?  It ca
n't be.
Then, trust, curiosity,
reflection, exploration
and looking inside ourselves too,
because exploration is not only
about what happens outside,
but also about what
happens inside us
and what happens inside the rest.
A very interesting thing
to do to be able to reflect better
is to listen.  It
's not a very common sport, is it?
Because, sometimes, what
we do is have monologues for two.
Or, sometimes, when we talk to someone,
we are more busy
preparing an answer
to win the argument
than understanding
exactly what the other person is like.  We
could say
that a very convenient sport
would be to try to truly understand,
with true curiosity,
how someone
completely different from us thinks,
someone with whom we share
absolutely nothing.
If we are able to feel curious
about understanding someone completely different, we will
probably become more confident.
It is a highly recommended sport.
Oh, how good.  What you
're saying,
if I understand you correctly,
is that security
depends more on us
than on controlling our environment,
which, in the end, is uncontrollable.
But now let's get back to being a father.
Those of us who are parents and have children, our
children, in the end,
are not as much within our control
as we would like.
So, how can we guarantee...?
Well, I don't know if the word is guarantee,
but how can we help
our children
gain that security?
In other words, is there any way
that we can do things
that help them have
all these tools
that will help them with this security,
with the calm that you mentioned before?
Note that sometimes we confuse terms.  I
often say that control
is a substitute for security.
A substitute...
Let's see, it
's not the worst thing we can have,
but it's not very good either
because, when unforeseen events occur,
and life sometimes
gets a little original,
control is useless to us.
People who function very much
through control
need everything to be predictable.
And, when they come across things
that are out of the ordinary, they are
disarmed
because they have no practice in improvising,
in being creative, in finding their own way in life,
in experimenting... They have
never done that.
We are always in control.
Then,
raising children from a controlling perspective
must be a nightmare
because you will live in constant anxiety.
In addition, children,
each one of whom is different,
who go through many stages, who
have to face
many difficulties... You
have to go with the flow.
Let's get back to sailing.  We
don't sail by taking the helm and saying,
"This is how it will be,
regardless of how the sea gets."
No.
We will have to maneuver
so that it can adapt.
And I don't think it's about
putting children in a bubble
or exposing them,
as I think we're exposing them
to social media too early,
or to things that they
're not ready to take on.  There
must be something in the middle.
One thing that helps develop
security in children,
I'll use a psychological word that
we sometimes use,
is the ability to mentalize the child.
This means that I am able to see
that my son is not a clone of me
who will do
everything I think he should do,
or who will be what I was not,
or any of that,
but that he is a little person
who has his own mind
and, even though he is very small,
he has a perspective on the world, he
has a way of seeing things.
And I sense it, I understand it
and I think about what he thinks.
If I have several children,
I know that they are different
and each one experiences things
in their own way,
and I can take into account their
personalities and abilities.
If I'm able to look at my son like this,
he'll be able to look at himself like this,
he'll understand when things happen to him.
Through the way
we look at them,
they will be able to look at themselves.
And they will also learn
something very important,
which is the ability to look at the other person
as a different person.
So,
this ability to mentalize,
to understand the child's mind,
so that the child can learn
to also understand
how the minds of others work,
is a superpower.  It
is important
for a child to feel a sense of being
loved unconditionally.
That, whether he does well, whether he does badly,
whether he achieves something,
whether he doesn't achieve something, he is
equally esteemed
and equally valuable.
And that, if he has a need, there
will be someone he can turn to,
and that person will be there
consistently.
Not every day is perfect, in the same mood, with
perfectly combed hair,
we are human beings and that is normal.
But he will feel that he can trust
that there is someone who values him for who he is,
who asks him for things that are reasonable
for his age,
because sometimes
we ask children for things
that do not correspond to their age
or we do not give them
the responsibility
that does come with their age.
Look, a child who lives
with very worried parents
is sometimes unprotected
because he sees his parents so worried
that he doesn't dare
tell them worrying things
so as not to worry them even more.
These types of paradoxes occur.
Then, we need to feel
that our parents will be there
no matter what
and that, even if we do wrong, we will
not lose their affection.  They
will correct us, they will tell us
that it is wrong, of course,
but that the affection is total
and guaranteed,
no matter what happens
and no matter how it works.  I
hear you speak,
and when I've heard you speak
on other occasions
and read your books, you
also talk
about the need to reflect
and educate ourselves about emotions,
which is something that, probably,
my parents' generation didn't do
and that in my generation we
may try,
perhaps, with little success, but we try.
What is it like to learn to reflect
on your own emotions?
What you were saying
about how our children will
learn to reflect on things
based on the way
we look at them.
I believe that there has always been
emotional education
and it has always existed in families
and, in fact, it is the place where learning takes place.
Now, also in schools,
but not in books,
but how the teacher realizes
or doesn't realize how the kids are
and how, more or less, he
manages to regulate his own stress,
that we have teachers,
poor things, a little stressed too.
This is the true school
of emotions, what
happens in relationships
with the people
around you
while you are growing up.
Man, if we know how
this emotional issue works
and learn a little about
the rules of the brain's game,
maybe we can realize things
that we may have been dragging
from our families,
because in each family
these things are managed in a different way.
An example is hugs.
There are families that define themselves as:
"We don't hug,"
as if they were a tribe.
And some of these people,
curiously enough, when they have children,
do dare to hug them because,
somehow,
they sense that perhaps they themselves
don't feel very comfortable,
but their children
do need it.
And thanks to their children, they
get used to giving
and receiving hugs,
which is something very useful
for regulating our emotions.
They have created a tribe:
the hug tribe.
Yes.  They change a little
to a new way of working.  We
can also learn
other ways of functioning,
but it's complicated
because parents also have
our stories, right?
And also, sometimes,
we haven't grown in security.  That's why
I believe that the best thing we
can do for our children
is to work to grow
our own security,
rather than learning 50 techniques
or reading 50 books on how to be parents,
because that
sometimes stresses us out more,
otherwise how can we
feel more secure.
Let's go back to the same point:
less looking at the environment and more
working on ourselves.
But, look, you mentioned something
that sometimes
creeps in from families,
and you also mentioned,
at another point in the conversation,
traumatic situations.
These
truly traumatic situations,
that is, which mark
a turning point in some lives, do they
have a solution?
Yes, of course.
This is what you dedicate yourself to.
Otherwise,
my profession would be meaningless.  Do
wounds heal?
Yes, of course they heal.
Sometimes, alone,
most of the time, luckily.
Emotional wounds also
heal over time.
And other times not,
emotional wounds...
But, since they are not visible,
we think we can pretend they are
not there and cover them up,
and sometimes we need to help
a little to heal them.
Sometimes, not only do we not help them
heal, but we scratch, we
rub salt in the wounds, we get
angry with ourselves
for being there...
And then it gets more complicated.
But there are two issues.
One is, if something happens to me,
the impact that this could have on me.
If this is not resolved,
it can have a
very significant influence, sometimes lasting for years,
and it can be resolved,
regardless of how much time passes.
But when we work, we
not only take this into account,
but also
the person's attachment style.
And attachment style
means how it works with
respect to the issue of security.
If a person has a secure attachment, they
are more able to reflect,
they are more able to trust, they
are more able to learn from experience,
and they are more able to establish relationships.
We talk a lot about one's things,
but security
cannot be learned in isolation.  We must
are times when we wear it
at home
because we grew up with parents
who were quite confident people.
Later we will talk about the difference
between confident and convinced,
but so as not to lose the thread...
And other times, perhaps,
our parents
were not confident people
and could not teach us
a language they did not know,
but we can learn it later.
And this security will also help us
resolve these traumas,
and even when
potentially traumatic things happen to us,
we will be able to bear it better, we
will be able to face
these kinds of experiences better.
It's a combination of both.
If something happens to a child,
the parents are a cushion.
In some families,
unfortunately, a mattress with spikes,
and in others, a soft mattress,
and we must try to be a soft mattress
so that, when things happen to them,
these things
don't affect them as much.
But things happen
and we need to help them deal with them.
But you said you were going to explain to me
the difference between sure and convinced,
and I won't get up from my chair
until you explain it to me.
Sometimes, we think that a confident person
is someone who says things like that.  Do
you think Donald Trump
is a safe person?
Yes, it seems so.  It
seems so, but it wouldn't be
the definition of a confident person at all.
He's an arrogant, dogmatic person, right?
A confident person
is a person who doubts.
Not that he doubts everything, we are
not usually good at extremes,
but he is a person who doubts
because, if he doesn't,
he is a person who doesn't learn.
And, if we don't learn,
we are always in the same place,
and that is not security, it is entrenching ourselves
in my convictions.
Many times,
very convinced people
are deeply insecure people
who say things in capital letters
so that others
don't shake them.
How good.
We see what we need to do to learn
to analyze these emotions,
but what happens if we are not able
to analyze
our own emotions?
What dangers exist,
if any?
The entire emotional mechanism is there
so that we know
what things mean,
what we need,
and, furthermore, they must lead us to
seek what we need.
Emotions
really have this function,
each one their own.
If we
don't follow the rules of the game,
so to speak,
trying to avoid...
I can't help but feel afraid, it
would be like saying:
"I want to avoid having lungs."
Well, I can't.
Every emotion has a function,
they all have meaning.
So, trying to avoid them,
trying to control them...
If I try to control an emotion
it's like trying to hold a cat very tightly.
Things will happen,
but they probably
won't be very convenient.  There
are times when we don't even realize
that emotions are there.
Another word
that we use is "alexithymia",
which describes people
who don't have an emotional vocabulary,
who don't realize...
Emotions are
something very confusing for them
or they wouldn't even know how to define them.
These people
tend to somatize much more,
to express through the body,
because through the emotional aspect
they are not able to explain to someone:
"I am bad",
because they would not know what to say.
Then, poor emotional management
is very unprofitable
because it causes emotions to get stuck,
blocked.
For example,
if I control them or suppress them,
which sometimes we
push so much down
that we don't even realize they're there,
we put them under the rug,
the rug gets bigger, I
put another rug on top of it...
And, when I can't take it anymore,
then I start drinking,
because it's the only way I can find,
or taking drugs or medications,
which we take a lot of anxiolytics.
We are trying to numb ourselves
from emotions.
If we were to ventilate them little by little, they
would not accumulate.
And then there are mechanisms
that are already "I can't take it anymore",
that sometimes,
literally, our fuses blow,
our head disconnects completely
and, sometimes, we
even put things in drawers,
in compartments,
and we try never to open them.
Sometimes, with certain emotions,
there are people who say:
"I never want to get angry."
It's impossible.
There are times when we get angry.
So, what do I do?
I keep going, I keep going, I keep going and
, every now and then, I explode.
And when I explode, I
feel terrible because I say:
"If I never want to get angry,
how can I get like this? It's not possible."  And
we do some cycles.
Then, there are people who have
aggressive behaviors, sometimes,
precisely
because they contain this anger.  It
's not the only reason,
there are many other reasons.
Or we can enter a depression
if what we do with the emotion
is turn it around and around and around
because, with each turn we turn it around,
we sink deeper and deeper.
Or because perhaps
this anger that we don't express gets
blocked
and we can develop physical problems.
Sometimes,
our entire body contracts
from all the tension
that we can't release through natural means.
If I have good emotional management,
everything flows.
We said before
that emotions are disposable,
so to speak.
If I let them come and listen to them,
I see what they mean,
if they tell me I
need something, I look for it,
these emotions go away.
This happens with sadness.
If something happens to us, we
lose someone, it
's normal to feel sad,
but,
since emotions are invisible...
Sometimes, we say:
"I don't want to be sad, I
don't have to be sad"
or "I'll keep working non-stop
so as not to connect with this sadness."
And what is sadness doing?
A deposit down here
of radioactive waste
that, the day it comes,
will come and I won't know what to do with it.
On the other hand, if I have lost someone,
I get sad, I cry, I
talk about it, I explain it to someone who
perhaps has also had a loss
and can resonate with me,
maybe they give me a hug...
The best thing that dissolves sadness
is the hug of someone
who understands what you are going through.
Notice that, sometimes, in families,
someone has been lost and some for others:
I won't explain anything to you
so that you don't get sad, and
the other one won't either...
And, in the end, what would be the
healthiest thing we could do,
which is to share this sadness,
is precisely what we prevent ourselves from doing.  We
are talking, it is true, about fears,
but I don't know if, perhaps, there are
also a series
of generational fears
that accompany us.  I do
n't know if this question
is perhaps a bit grandiloquent,
but I would like you to explain to me
what fears you see
that we have now in the 21st century,
in the generation we live in.  Are
there some characteristics of fear
that somehow define
the era we are living in?
There are fears that are universal:
things that are dangerous,
animals...
Many phobias are animal phobias
because, clearly, it
's not appropriate for you to approach a snake.  We are
afraid of loneliness
because we are social beings,
although many people end up,
supposedly, adapting to it,
but one never adapts well to it.
We fear death
because,
even though there are some people
who seek it at a certain moment
as a solution, we are
not prepared for it.
We are here
to try to enjoy the life we have
as much as possible.
But then there are very personal fears.
I believe
that the history of our fears,
the history of the things
that have scared us
and, above all,
the fears that we have not been able to resolve,
are what shapes
what we are afraid of.
I think what we
can all resonate with
is that it is an emotion
that we have all felt at some point.
At some points we
may have unresolved fears.
I think it's
practically impossible to reach adults
without anything having affected you
or nothing having influenced you.
And they are very, very personal fears,
but if we shared them
with another person,
perhaps we would see that they have a lot in common
with the fears of others.
Well, nothing, Anabel,
thank you very much for this talk.
I enjoyed it very much.
I leave with many powerful ideas, I
leave inspired.
I hope we can
chat again soon.  It has
been a
very interesting joint reflection.